בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is ל"ב Lamed Bet בבא
בתרא Bava Batra 32, we pick up at the bottom of ל"א
עמוד ב' Lamed Aleph Amud Bet and
דתנן, detnan, אלא משום דתליא באשלי רברבי, ela mishum detalya be'ashelai ravrevei,
it is one, two, three, four, five, six, eight lines on the
bottom right before the little ג' Gimmel in the half parentheses and
we were just with a story where there were witnesses, one person
had witnesses about that he had חזקה chazaka years plus that it
was his father's, the other just had witnesses that it was חזקה
chazaka years. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, well, you negate the
חזקה chazaka year witnesses against one another and you award it to
the person who has the witnesses that it was just the fathers.
The גמרא Gemara had some whole discussion about that, but that was
רב נחמן's Rav Nachman position. And then came along other witnesses that
said that it belonged to the other person's father, which got us
back to even ground. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, okay, we
originally awarded it to the guy with the witnesses of his father,
now we will take it out and leave it open for debate,
like we won't give it to either one, we'll see exactly what
we do, כל דאלים גבר Kol de'alim gavar the גמרא Gemara will
say, and we're prepared to reverse our ruling now that new witnesses
have shown up and we're not concerned for זילותא דבי דינא, ziluta
de'bei dina, we're not concerned that this will be ill repute on
the בית דין. Beis Din. So that was then challenged with a
debate of תנאים tannaim or whatever, a position of תנאים tannaim that
made it sound like we are concerned with זילותא דבי דינא ziluta
de'bei dina and we don't reverse ourselves once we've made a particular
ruling. רב נחמן Rav Nachman seemed at first to concede that fine,
I won't reverse myself, and then he went out and he reversed
himself and he showed that he wasn't concerned with זילותא דבי דינא.
ziluta de'bei dina. So we'll pick up with that. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, נפק עובדא, nafak ovda, I guess we'll start
ten lines from the bottom, מאן דחזא man dechaza סבר savar טעות
הוא בידיה, taus hu beyadei, he
made a mistake, he forgot about the
fact that this position was
disproven, ולא היא velo hi but that's not true, אלא משום דתליא
באשלי רברבי, ela mishum detalya be'ashelai ravrevei,
he hung it on these very large oak trees, meaning he had
good supports to back up his position that we're not concerned with
זילותא דבי דינא, ziluta de'bei dina, we're more concerned with doing the
truth than that it should look bad how we're acting. And if
now there are contrary witnesses, even if the resolution interestingly is not
to award it to the other person, right, you might say of
course we're not going to be concerned with זילותא דבי דינא ziluta
de'bei dina if the witnesses prove that it belongs to ראובן Reuven
and not שמעון, Shimon, of course we're now going to do the
right thing and give it to ראובן. Reuven. But in this case
everything's just been neutralized and we're just going to put it back
into no man's land. So that might you just say it might
be best just to leave things the way they are. And even
here רב נחמן Rav Nachman says no we're not concerned with זילותא
דבי דינא, ziluta de'bei dina, we are even though we're not going
to now know yet whose it is and we're not going to
award it to anybody, we're still going to reverse our awarding it
to שמעון Shimon if there's no longer a reason that שמעון Shimon
should have it.
And we will rule accordingly and not be concerned with זילותא דבי
דינא. ziluta de'bei dina. And he has strong support.
Excuse me. So let's see what his support is.
אלא דתליא באשלי רברבי. ela detalya be'ashelai ravrevei. דתנן, detnan, we learned
in the משנה, Mishna, רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer, אין מעלין
לכהונה על פי עד אחד. ein ma'alin lekhahuna al pi ed echad.
If there's a question if somebody's a legitimate כהן, kohen, there's a
rumor that he might be like the son of a גרושה grusha
or חלוצה chalutza and a חלל, chalal, then one witness is not
enough to establish him as a good כהן. kohen. We'll see in
a minute that that means when there's a really established basis to
think he's not good, you cannot correct that on the basis of
one witness.
אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rebbe Elazar, אימתי, eimatai, when is this true?
במקום שיש עוררין, bimkom sheyesh orein, when there's a real critique, when
there's a real report against his status, and we're going to see
that that report is going to be based on two witnesses actually
are testifying. Then one witness obviously won't be enough to counter it.
אבל במקום שאין עוררין, aval bimkom she'ein orein,
but if it's not real people challenging his status, it's just some
rumor but it's not like there's two witnesses, then מעלין לכהונה על
פי עד אחד, ma'alin lekhahuna al pi ed echad, one witness is
good enough to dispel the rumor and to establish him as a
כהן. kohen. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר משום רבי שמעון בן מנסיא,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya, מעלין לכהונה
על פי עד אחד. ma'alin lekhahuna al pi ed echad.
You can do it, so says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel, you can do it based on one witness. So the
גמרא Gemara says, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל היינו רבי אלעזר, Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel hainu Rebbe Elazar, that's the same, they're both saying you
could do it with one witness, presumably they would both agree you
can't do it against a real עוררין, orein, but you can do
it against a rumor, so they're both agreeing that one witness is
good against some weak problem but not against a strong problem. Where
are they disagreeing? All right, so so far it's not clear at
all what this has to do with our case about זילותא דבי
דינא, ziluta de'bei dina, but we will see. וכי תימא, vechi teima,
עיר חד ir chad איכא בינייהו, ika beiniyahu, maybe here's the difference,
about whether how it works against a... ill report
against him from one witness, meaning one against isn't good enough against
two, what's the דין din about one against one? Here's maybe how
we can frame the debate. רבי אליעזר סבר עיר חד. Rabbi Eliezer
savar ir chad. Rabbi Eliezer says, you know, when there's עוררין, urin,
now עוררין urin the language is in the plural, but he will
read them to say when there's any
established claim that he's invalid, he's a בן גרושה, Ben Grusha, then
עד אחד ed echad can't counter it. So an עד אחד ed
echad can't counter another עד אחד. ed echad. And that's what he's
saying. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel top of ל"ב
עמוד א', lamed bet amud aleph, סבר עיר תרי. savar ir trei.
No, unless it's a really established claim against him of שני עדים,
sheinei eidim, then that one עד ed can't dispel, but one עד
ed could dispel one עד. ed. Why would one against one be
good? Again, maybe they just neutralize and then you'd be back to
your חזקת כשרות. chasakas kashrus. Okay, so maybe that's the debate. The
debate is can one עד ed dispel some general rumor? Can one
עד ed dispel one עד? ed? That's debated and we'll say רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer will say he cannot, and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel will say that he can. Fine. Okay, so
that but we got a problem. ואמר רבי יוחנן דברי הכל אין
עיר פחות משנים, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan divei hakol ein ir pachos mishnayim,
but Rabbi Yochanan says and והש"ס v'haShas says I don't know where
Rabbi Yochanan says it, but anyway Rabbi Yochanan says no, if it's
not a negative report coming from two witnesses, then it does not
really count as an עיר. ir. And therefore the claim would be
that everybody would say if it's only one witness saying that he's
an invalid כהן, kohen, one witness would be enough to dispel it
and get you back to status quo. So if they can't be
debating, you know, the status of one, everybody obviously would agree one
against two wouldn't work. And now we're saying that everybody would agree
that one against one would work. So what's the debate here about
the believability of one עד ed to recognize somebody as a legitimate
כהן? kohen? So that's going to push us to read it as
a case relevant to this issue of זילותא דבי דינא. zilusa d'vei
dina. And there's going to be a lot we're going to squeeze
into
these very terse statements. So let's take a look. אלא, Ella,
says גמרא Gemara says, עיר תרי, ir trei, fine. It is two
people are saying that he was a בן גרושה בן חלוצה. ben
grusha ben chaluza. And there's still some debate about believing this עד
ed that says that he's good. Now how could you believe one
עד ed that says that he's good against שני עדים sheinei eidim
that say that he's no good? Because here's the case. והכא במאי
עסקינן כגון דמחזקינן ליה באבוה דהאי דכהן הוא. V'hacha b'mai askinan, kegon
d'machzikinan lei b'avuah d'hai dekohein hu. We start with knowing that this
guy's father was a כהן. kohen. So we start we have a
חזקת כשרות. chasakas kashrus. Okay, that's going to allow one to one
to neutralize, that's sort of how we were explaining it before, we
start with a חזקת כשרות. chasakas kashrus. ונפיק עליה קלא דבן גרושה
בן חלוצה. V'nafik alei kala de'ben grusha ben chaluza.
But there's some rumor, some unfounded rumor that he's a בן גרושה
ben grusha and בן חלוצה. ben chaluza. ואחתיניה v'achtineih
and we said okay you know what, don't serve as a כהן
kohen at least not until we can clarify this matter. We didn't
definitely rule that he was a בן גרושה בן חלוצה, ben grusha
ben chaluza, but we sort of put him
on administrative leave until we can determine his status. ואתא עד אחד
ואמר דכהן הוא V'asa ed echad v'amar dekohein hu and came along
a כהן kohen this testified actually that he's a כהן kohen and
that's עד אחד ed echad against just some unfounded rumor. ואסקיניה v'askineih
and then we fine that was enough to dispel the rumor and
we established him as a good עד, ed, good כהן kohen and
he could go ahead and serve.
All good, nobody disagrees with that. One עד ed against some unfounded
rumor. ואתו בי תרי ואמרי דבן גרושה וחלוצה. V'asu bei trei v'amri
de'ben grusha v'chaluza.
Then comes along two and says he's a בן גרושה ben grusha
and בן חלוצה ben chaluza and that's the עוררין. urin. Remember everybody
said that for there to be an issue and for us to
talk about עוררין urin it has to be two. So we've got
שני עדים sheinei eidim now that have actually said that he's a
פסול כהן. posul kohen. ואחתיניה v'achtineih and then we once again deposed
him and here we sort of said we're ruling that you're a
פסול כהן, posul kohen, you can't do the עבודה. avodah.
ואתא עד אחד ואמר דכהן הוא V'asa ed echad v'amar dekohein hu
and now another עד ed came and said he was a good
כהן. kohen. So you have that one עד ed that says he's
good can match up with the one עד ed earlier that said
he's good, right? So it says it was rumor,
one עד ed good, שני עדים sheinei eidim bad, one עד ed
good. So now the one עד ed good and the one עד
ed good can combine and neutralize the שני עדים sheinei eidim that
say that it was bad. That's at least what should be able
to happen. And if one עד ed can work against one עד
ed and neutralize it and get us back to status quo, then
שני עדים sheinei eidim can work against שני עדים, sheinei eidim, neutralize
and get us back to status quo. So in theory everybody should
be able to agree that we can get this guy back to
status quo and be considered a good כהן. kohen. But let's see
what happens.
ודכולי עלמא מצטרפין עדות V'duchulei alma mitztarfin eidut and everybody would agree
that you could combine the one עד ed that said good earlier
with the one עד ed that said good later and now you
have שני עדים sheinei eidim that say good in principle.
והכא במיחש לזילותא דבי דינא קמיפלגי V'hacha b'meichash l'zilusa d'vei dina kamifligi
and the debate would be are you concerned about belittling the court.
considered with the זילותא zilus of בית דין beis din because you
keep on reversing yourself back and forth. רבי אליעזר סבר כיון דנחתינן
לא מסקינן ליה. Rabbi Eliezer savar keivan denachtinan lo maskinan lei. Rabbi
Eliezer says you don't believe that one עד eid against the over
the two bad, the two עדים eidim that say he's bad, you
don't believe the one עד eid good even plus the other one
עד eid good. Why not? Not because it's one against two, it's
really two against two, but because of this principle of זילותא דבי
דינא. zilusa d'vei dina. We're not going to keep on moving back
and forth and back and forth and therefore we're going to let
him retain his status as a פסול כהן pasul kohen because of
זילותא דבי דינא. zilusa d'vei dina. ורבן גמליאל סבר. Verabban Gamliel savar.
ורבן גמליאל Verabban Gamliel says no, you do believe the one עד,
eid, meaning one plus one you get two and two against two
and they've neutralized. אנן נחתינן ליה ואנן מסקינן ליה, Anan nachtinan lei
veanan maskinan lei, we took him deposed, took him off his post,
we can put him back on his post. ולזילותא דבי דינא לא
חיישינן, Ulezilusa d'vei dina lo chaishinan, we're not considered for the זילותא
zilusa of בית דין. beis din. So here, it's at least have
an issue of זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei dina as a מחלוקת
תנאים. machlokes tanaim. Okay, we're not done yet. That wouldn't be תליא
באשלי רברבי, talya bashlei ravrvei, that's only just one opinion. It's still
a מחלוקת תנאים. machlokes tanaim. Okay, but that's the way we're explaining,
that it's a debate of זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei dina based
on the one and then two and then another one good, two
bad and then another one good. I should by the way point
out, you know, obviously the question to ask here is why don't
we just start with one good, two bad, one good. Why do
we have to start with first there was a rumor, we deposed
him, one good, we put him back in his place, and that
makes it sound like the concern of זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei
dina might be that we're reversing ourselves twice. In the earlier case,
we were only reversing ourselves once. It makes it less exactly similar.
So רשב"ם ותוספות Rashbam ve-Tosafos have ways of saying that, that really
wasn't central to the point and we really could have just started
and said one, two and one. We didn't have to really start
with the case of saying that there was a rumor. We only
started with that case
to explain why the one who said good had to come forward
in the first place, why would he have come forward if there
wasn't a rumor to dispel. And the fact that we actually said
we deposed him, that wasn't really seen as a reversal as a
זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei dina in the beginning, because that was
just like I said administrative lead. It wasn't a real פסק. psak.
A זילותא zilusa problem is when you're reversing a real פסק. psak.
Okay, so bracket the fact that it started off with a rumor
and an עד אחד. eid echad. Bottom line is, there were two
עדים eidim said no good and now there are two עדים eidim
that say good. Will we reverse ourselves or not because of the
concern of זילותא דבי דינא? zilusa d'vei dina? And that's the debate.
Okay, the problem of course is as the גמרא Gemara is about
to ask, if that's really what was going on, why did we
have to complicate it with one, two and one, not just say
two and two, which is what the גמרא Gemara now asks. מתקיף
לה רב אשי, Matkif lah Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi challenges, אי הכי
מאי איריא חד אפילו תרי נמי. ei hachi mai irya chad afilu
trei nami. So why did you have to say one good, two
bad, one good, זילותא דבי דינא? zilusa d'vei dina? Just say two
said bad, we said he was a פסול כהן, pasul kohen, then
two say good and can we go ahead and reverse it. Since
it didn't say that and it made it about one עד, eid,
clearly there's something here about the one עד eid and it has
nothing to do with זילותא דבי דינא, zilusa d'vei dina, because the
זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei dina would not have been limited to
a case of there being one עד eid separated from the other
one עד. eid. So אלא אמר רב אשי, ella amar Rav Ashi,
so here's how Rav Ashi explains it and this is now how
it's going to be a support of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. דכולי
עלמא לא חיישינן לזילותא דבי דינא. dekulei alma lo chaishinan lezilusa d'vei
dina. The way to explain this is that everybody in principle agrees
that we are not concerned for זילותא דבי דינא. zilusa d'vei dina.
That if two עדים eidim said bad and then two עדים eidim
said good, even if we had deposed him, we would put him
back on his post. And we don't care about זילותא דבי דינא.
zilusa d'vei dina. And that's implicit in this whole debate. The only
issue here is do we really have two עדים eidim saying that
he's good. So it's we're switching the variables. As opposed to the
variable being זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei dina and the question being
about, you know, and everybody agreeing that you combine the first good
עד eid and the last good עד, eid, we're switching it. Everybody
agrees that זילותא דבי דינא zilusa d'vei dina is not a problem,
that's the constant, and the variable, the debate, is can you combine
the one עד eid before and the one עד eid later.
ובהא בצירוף עדות קמיפלגי. Uveha betzeiruf eidus kemeifligai. Here they're debating can
you combine the one עד eid earlier and the one עד eid
later, which is means what? So, one עד eid said good, two
עדים eidim said bad, one עד eid said good. If you could
combine those two עדים eidim that came separately and individually, then it
would be two good against two bad, neutralized, we're not concerned for
זילותא דבי דינא, zilusa d'vei dina, we would restore him to his
post. And that has everybody here, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel saying we're not concerned for זילותא דבי דינא zilusa
d'vei dina and that is why
רב נחמן Rav Nachman finds support for his position. So what is
their debate? Their debate is because these עדים, eidim, this one עד
eid and the one עד eid were separate and they didn't come
together, can they now be combined even when they come separately. And
that's the debate. זילותא דבי דינא Zilusa d'vei dina not an issue.
We'll reverse ourselves. The only question is do these two separate עדים
eidim combine. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאים, Uveplugta dehanei tanaim, and it's debate and
it's linked to the same debate as the following debate of תנאים.
tanaim. דתניא, detanya, we learnt
in a ברייתא, beraisa, לעולם אין עדות מצטרפת עד שיהיו שניהם כאחד.
leolam ein edus mitztarefes ad sheyihyu sheneihem ke'echad. רבי יהושע בן קרחה
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha אומר, omer, אפילו בזה אחר זה. afilu bezeh
achar zeh. So this ברייתא beraisa actually isn't relevant for us, but
it's just a nice related debate, the first half of it, which
is: one witness says Reuven borrowed a hundred dollars from Shimon on
Monday, and another עד eid says Reuven borrowed a hundred dollars from
Shimon on Tuesday. So, do they combine or not? So the first
position says no, they're not testifying to the same thing, לעולם אין
עדות מצטרפת עד שיהיו שניהם כאחד, leolam ein edus mitztarefes ad sheyihyu
sheneihem ke'echad, they both have to say the same event took place.
The second position, רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says
they're both saying Reuven owes a hundred dollars to Shimon, the specifics
don't matter, okay, אפילו בזה אחר זה. afilu bezeh achar zeh. Now
that's not our issue, that's what they're testifying about what they saw.
We're dealing with a different case,
which is the second part of the ברייתא, beraisa, which is actually
a משנה. mishna. אין עדותם מתקיימת בבית דין עד שיעידו שניהם כאחד.
ein edusam miskayemes beveise din ad sheya'idu sheneihem ke'echad. The תנא קמא,
tanna kamma, a new case, תנא קמא tanna kamma says, for witnesses
to be considered two, they have to come and bring their testimony
together and be accepted as a unit of two in בית דין.
beis din. רבי נתן Rabbi Nassan אומר, omer, שומעין דבריו של זה
היום וכשיבוא חברו למחר שומעין דבריו. shomin devarav shel zeh hayom uchesheyavo
chavero lemachar shomin devarav. No, even if one guy comes, Reuven comes
on Sunday, and we don't know that there's a Shimon who's following,
we just accept Reuven's testimony, and then on Monday or on Wednesday
Shimon shows up and he has the same thing to say, we
accept his separate testimony separately. Even though we accepted one as עד
אחד eid echad and one as עד אחד, eid echad, now we're
able to combine them and that creates two עדים. edim. And that
is the debate here of countering the combined testimony that this person
is a בן גרושה, ben grusha, can you combine the two separate
עד אחד eid echad testimonies that he's כשר? kasher? And that is
the debate. But everybody agrees we're not concerned for זילוטא דבי דינא,
zilusa debei dina, and that was רב נחמן's Rav Nachman position. Now,
we should acknowledge that in this case, not being concerned of זילוטא
דבי דינא zilusa debei dina means you're restoring this guy to his
rightful post, and that's why we will not let concerns of our
perception of us as a בית דין beis din get in the
way of meting out true justice and letting this guy restore his
rightful post. Okay, that is different from רב נחמן's Rav Nachman case
where he took the land away from the guy he awarded it
to, but he didn't award it to the other person, it was
just left in no man's land. That would be a case you
might more reasonably say we should be concerned and let things stay
the way they are until we have good reason to do them
otherwise. But anyway, that is how רב נחמן Rav Nachman backed his
position. Let's continue, yet another real case. ההוא דאמר לחבריה, hahu de'amar
lechaverei, somebody said to his friend, מאי בעית בהאי ארעא, mai bayis
behai ara, what are you doing in this land? This is my
land. אמר ליה מנך זבינתה. amar lei minach zevintah. So Reuven said
to Shimon, what are you doing in the land? And Shimon said,
what do you mean, I bought it from you. והא שטרא, veha
shtra, and here's my שטר. shtar.
Top of ל"ב ע"א, lamed beis amud aleph, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so Reuven said to Shimon, שטר זיופא הוא, shtar zayfa hu, that's
a forged שטר. shtar. גחין ולחיש ליה לרבא, gechin velachish lei leRava,
so Shimon went and he whispered to רבא, Raba, who apparently was
the דיין dayan of the case, אין שטר זיופא הוא, in shtar
zayfa hu,
yeah, it really is a forged שטר. shtar. It's a very, very
good forgery and I did it, I'll admit that. מיהו שטר מעליא
הוה לי ואירכס, mihu shtar ma'alya hava li ve'irkas, but you know
what, I had actually a good שטר, shtar, I did have a
שטר shtar for that that he owed me the money. I think
I got confused who is Reuven and Shimon here. No, I got
it right. Shimon got, owed me money. I did have a שטר
shtar that I bought the land from Reuven, but I lost it.
ואמינא, va'amina, and therefore I said to myself, אינקט האי בידאי כל
דהו, einkat hai beyadai kol dehu, let me at least use this
forged שטר shtar and that'll make it because it'll replace the genuine
שטר shtar that I actually had, okay? So he conceded that he
did not have a good שטר, shtar, it was a forgery, but
he, it was such a good forgery that had he not conceded
it, it would have passed muster. And but he admitted to רבא
Raba that it was a forgery and he said, yeah, because I
actually had a genuine שטר shtar and I lost it. אמר רבא
מה לי לשקר אי בעי אמר ליה שטר מעליא הוא. amar Raba
mah li leshaker ei bayei amar lei shtar ma'alya hu.
So רבא Raba said this is a classic מיגו. miggo. It was
such a good forgery that Shimon could have denied what Reuven said,
said it's not a forgery, it's genuine, and could have gotten away
with it, and we would have said it's a שטר shtar on
the land. So the fact that he admitted that he had forged
it, okay, but he could have gotten away with it, so he's
believed that he had a genuine שטר shtar and he lost it,
because he just could have been quiet and could have gotten away
with the forgery. That's a classic מיגו, miggo, he didn't have to
lie to
say he's obviously telling the truth because if he wanted to lie
he just would have gone with the forgery and not said anything.
אמר ליה רב יוסף, amar lei Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said to
רבא, Raba, אמאי סמכת אהאי שטרא האי שטרא חספא בעלמא הוא, amai
samacht ahai shtra hai shtra chaspa be'alma hu, how can you rely
on this שטר? shtar? This שטר shtar is a piece of pottery.
Now what does that mean? Obviously the שטר shtar is false because
he's admitting that it's false. He still could have gotten away with
saying that it was true, so isn't that how's that different than
any other מיגו? miggo? Believe me that I bought it that it
was my father's because I could have claimed that I bought it
from you. Okay, but why should I believe you that it's your
father's? You're right now admitting you
know... Believe me that it's my father's because I could have claimed
I could have bought it from you. But you can't claim you
could have bought it from you because you're just because you're because
you told me you didn't buy it from me, you tell me
it's your father's. I know, but if I had wanted to lie,
I could have said that I bought it from you. So what
I'm admitting to now that I could have said I bought it
from you can't be used as a proof against my claim that
it's my father's. I could have gotten away with this lie if
I had wanted to lie by saying that I bought it from
you and therefore you should believe me that I'm telling the truth
that it's my father's. So how is that different here? Yes, I
am admitting to you that it is a forgery, okay, and but
believe me when I say that I had an honest a real
שטר shtar and that you know and I lost it because I
could have said that this was real. The fact that I am
now admitting that it isn't real, admitting that it's a forgery, it
doesn't matter. I didn't have to admit that. I could have said
it was real. So since I could have said it's real, you
should believe me now that I'm telling you that it's a forgery
but that I had a real one that got lost. How is
this different than any other מיגו? migo? Not exactly clear. So תוספות
Tosafot says one answer which fits sort of well with the conclusion
of the גמרא, Gemara, which has to do with the fact like
okay, maybe it is a מיגו, migo, but maybe it's a מיגו
migo doesn't work, you know, to take money away from somebody. It
worked to establish something that's in your possession, not to take property
away from somebody that it's in their possession. And since by land
we always consider it to be in the possession of the person
that first, you know, owned it, that not the one because what
does it mean? It's not like it's in your pocket. It's not
like chattel that it's physically on your person in your possession. Land
is always in the possession of the person that we know was
the last one to rightfully own it. So therefore maybe you know
what רב יוסף Rav Yosef is saying is fine, you've got a
מיגו. migo. You could have gotten away with saying it if you
had wanted to lie, but that's not enough to take it away
from the person who we know was the rightful the previous rightful
owner. That's one way of reading it. It's not exactly what he
says. He says it's a piece of pottery. It doesn't sound like
he's saying yes, it's a good מיגו, migo, but מיגו migo doesn't
work להוציא lehotzi to take it away from the person who was
the previous rightful owner who is the one who's considered in possession.
What makes more sense is that
it's giving a person strength in בית דין Beit Din on the
basis of the fact that they committed a forgery, right? If I
say believe me that this is my father's because I could have
claimed that it's that I you know that I that I that
I bought it from you, I'm saying that I'm totally an honest
man of total integrity. Actually my whole מיגו migo is that I'm
totally honest. You should believe me that I am as honest as
the driven snow. And then when I say it's my father's, it
was totally my father's. Because if I had wanted to be a
liar, I could have come up with a really good lie and
I could have said I bought it from you and here are
the years of חזקה, chazaka, etc. etc. So it's all about me
being honest, right? Here, it's about accepting the fact that I did
a terrible thing, that I forged a document. You should believe me
that I actually had a שטר shtar because if I wanted to
lie I could have gotten away with it with a document that
I am telling you that I forged. So you have already conceded
that you're a dishonest person who forges documents. Now all of a
sudden I'm supposed to believe you? So that's a better way of
understanding it. He's telling you this is a piece of pottery and
on the basis of him telling you that this is a you
know that this is a piece of junk, you're now supposed to
give that's supposed to give him believability? So that's at least רב
יוסף's Rav Yosef response. Seems like a pretty reasonable response. Okay,
let's the גמרא Gemara does not conclude, but we're not done yet.
Does not okay. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה, Hahu de'amar lei lechavreih, exact
same case. Somebody said to his friend, הב לי מאה זוזי דמסקנא
בך, Hav li mei'ah zuzei demaskana bach,
give me the hundred dollars that I lent you know I lent
you a hundred dollars, pay me up. והא שטרא, Veha shtra,
here's the שטר. shtar. אמר ליה, Amar lei, שטרא
זייפא הוא. shtra zaifa hu. So ראובן Reuven said to שמעון, Shimon,
give me the hundred dollars you owe me and שמעון Shimon said
that שטר shtar is a forgery. גחין ולחיש ליה לרבה, Gachin velachish
lei leRabbah, so ראובן Reuven then whispered to רבה, Rabbah, you know
he's right, the שטר shtar is a forgery, just like the previous
case. מיהו שטרא מעליא הוה לי, Mihu shtra ma'alya hava li, I
had a good שטר shtar ואירכס ve'irchas and I lost it ואמינא
אנקט האי בידי, ve'amina ekot hai beyadi, and I said let me
at least hold on to this שטר, shtar, it'll be something, and
that way you know and that's why I made up this forgery.
But the reality is is that I really did have a legitimate
שטר. shtar. So what's the story? So אמר רבה מה לו לשקר
אי בעי אמר ליה שטרא מעליא הוה לי. Amar Rabbah mah lo
leshaker i bei amar lei shtra ma'alya hava hu. So רבה Rabbah
says like he said before, he's got a מיגו. migo. He could
have gotten away with saying it was real. The fact that I
am now admitting that it isn't real, admitting that it's a forgery,
it doesn't matter. I didn't have to admit that. I could have
said it was real. Since I could have said it was real,
you should believe me now that I'm telling you that it's a
forgery but that I had a real one that got lost. How
is this different than any other מיגו? migo? Not exactly clear. אמר
ליה רב יוסף, amar lei Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef said,
אמאי קסמכת אהאי שטרא האי שטרא חספא בעלמא הוא? amai kasamchas a-hai
shtar hai shtar chaspa be'alma hu?
How could you rely on this שטרא? shtar? It's a piece of
pottery, which the best way I would like to read this is,
what do you mean we should believe him that he had a
good שטרא? shtar? This guy, the only reason we're believing him is
cause is cause he actually has done something terrible and he's made
a forgery. So now we should all of a sudden believe him?
The guy's a liar. By his own admission he's a liar. In
all the other cases of מיגו migo it's I could, if I
wanted to lie I could have lied, but I'm telling you I'm
saying the truth. Here, he's actually telling us that he's a liar.
So all of a sudden we're supposed to now believe him? That's
the nice way to read רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. Okay, same debate.
So, אמר רב אידי בר אבין הלכתא כוותיה דרבא בארעא והלכתא כוותיה
דרב יוסף בזוזי. amar Rav Idi bar Avin hilchesa kevasiah de-Rava be-ara
v-hilchesa kevasiah de-Rav Yosef be-zuzi. We rule like רבא Rabba when it
comes to land, in the case of the land, when he says
what are you doing on my land and he says I bought
it, here's the שטרא shtar and it's a forgery and I could
have gotten away with it, etc. In that case we say we
use his מיגו migo and we let him hold on to the
land.
But when in the רב יוסף Rav Yosef case,
when he has this forged שטרא shtar and he says but he
could have gotten away with it, we don't let him use the
מיגו migo and he's not able to operate on the שטרא shtar
and collect in the debt. So on the one case he can
use the false שטרא shtar based on a מיגו migo and hold
on to the land, but he can't use the false שטרא shtar
based on a מיגו migo and collect the debt.
והלכתא כוותיה דרב יוסף בזוזי. v-hilchesa kevasiah de-Rav Yosef be-zuzi. הלכתא כרבא
בארעא. hilchesa ke-Rava be-ara. Why? דהיכא דקיימא ארעא תיקו, de-heicha de-kaima ara
tiku, where the land is it should remain. Since the guy is
right now on the land and he's got the שטרא shtar and
he's got the מיגו, migo, he can keep the land in his
possession.
והלכתא כוותיה דרב יוסף בזוזי, v-hilchesa kevasiah de-Rav Yosef be-zuzi, but when
we rule like רב יוסף Rav Yosef with when it comes to
money, דהיכא דקיימי זוזי לוקמי, de-heicha de-kaimi zuzi lokmi, where the money
is let the money stay. The guy's got the שטרא, shtar, he's
got the מיגו migo with his forged שטרא. shtar. He can't use
the forged שטרא shtar to extract money. And this is more like
תוספות Tosafos is originally saying that actually this type of a מיגו,
migo, maybe it's a combination, you know, it's a weak מיגו migo
because it's based on a falsehood. So this type of a מיגו
migo you can use it to hold on to something, you can't
use it to extract something. So you can't use it to extract
the money in the case of the שטרא shtar of the debt
because it's a מיגו migo based on a forgery or maybe in
general we don't use מיגו migo to extract money. But you can
use it to hold on to the land in the case where
he's claiming that he bought the land. Now the problem with that
as I said earlier is that what this whole פרק perek is
based on is that when it comes to land, being physically present
on the land
doesn't
give you a חזקה. chazakah. Maybe doing three years makes it a
gives you a sense of it being in your possession, but anything
less than three years you're just physically there. It's not in your
it's under your control. The sense of control when it comes to
land has to do with who the last rightful owner is or
at least who the person who has been working on it for
the last three years is. Okay, but the fact that the גמרא
Gemara here says it is a weaker type of a you know
חזקה chazakah by land. Since you have this מיגו migo and you
have this שטרא shtar and you're right now the one sitting on
the land even though you haven't been there for three years, it
will be enough to hold on to it. So it's an interesting
combination of a מיגו migo based on a falsehood and maybe you
know and that will allow it to work well enough to let
you stay on the land even though your current presence on the
land normally is not something that's recognized as being in possession of
the land. Okay, so that's the sort of conclusion of the גמרא.
Gemara. One more case relating to that. ההוא ארבא, hahu arba, there
was a boat. Actually, excuse me, this is an ערב. ariv. Boat
is coming later. Okay, there was an ערב. ariv. דאמר ליה ללווה,
de-amar lei l-loveh, so an ערב ariv with his a guarantor said
to the lender. He was somebody that basically the creditor was allowed
to go to the guarantor, so we'll say the guarantor here is
ראובן Reuven and the borrower is שמעון. Shimon. And the creditor could
go to the guarantor to get his money collect to get his
loan paid up.
So the guarantor said to שמעון, Shimon, the guarantor said to ללווה,
l-loveh, הב לי מאה זוזי דפרעתי למלווה, hav li meah zuzi de-parati
l-malveh, I paid that creditor a hundred dollars. You had borrowed a
hundred dollars, I was your guarantor, I paid him up the hundred
dollars. Now you have to pay
me
back. Okay. ושטרא, v-shtar,
here's the שטרא shtar that the creditor gave me when I paid
him the hundred dollars which proves I paid up your debt. Here's
my receipt, I paid your debt for you, now you have to
pay me back.
אמר ליה, amar lei, so שמעון Shimon the borrower said, לא פרעתיך,
la paraticha, haven't I already paid you back for that money you
paid the
creditor? אמר, amar, he said back, לאו הדר שקלתיה מינאי, lav hadar
shakaltia minai, yes you did pay me the hundred dollars for the
debt I paid on your behalf, and then you turned around and
asked me to borrow the hundred dollars again. So actually when I'm
now asking you for the hundred dollars, you're right, it's not for
the original payment I paid on your behalf. But it's for the
hundred dollars you borrowed that you paid up, but it's for the
hundred dollars you borrowed afterwards. שדר רב אידי בר אבין Shadar Rav
Idi bar Avin לקמיה דאביי. Lekameh deAbaye. So רב אידי בר אבין
Rav Idi bar Avin sent this to אביי. Abaye. כי האי גוונא
מאי? Ki hai gavna mai? What's the story about this? Because in
a way, this is similar to the previous case, because he was
trying to collect the debt from the borrower with this שטר, shtar,
you know, that, the of the original debt. But what we're really
talking here is a new debt when שמעון Shimon lent ראובן Reuven
another hundred dollars. Okay, and he's trying to collect the new debt
based on the שטר shtar of the old debt that had already
been paid up.
So מאי? mai? שלח ליה אביי: Shelach leh Abaye: מאי תיבעי לך?
Mai tibei lach? What's your question? האי הוא דאמר, Hai hu de-amar,
you know, you're the one who says הלכתא כוותיה דרבה בארעא והלכתא
כוותיה דרב יוסף בזוזי. hilchata kevatchi de-Rabba be-ara ve-hilchata kevatchi de-Rav Yosef
be-zuzi. That we rule like
רבה Rabba when it comes to land, and we rule like רב
יוסף Rav Yosef when it comes to the money. And this is
a case of money, because, you know, the guarantor is trying to
collect the money from the borrower and it's an invalid שטר, shtar,
it's not maybe a forgery, but it's an invalid שטר. shtar. And
the מיגו migo that he didn't have to admit that he was
reusing the שטר, shtar, that מיגו migo should not help him to
collect the money. Ultimately, the שטר shtar is not valid, he's basing
his מיגו migo on that שטר, shtar, he can't use it to
collect money like we said before, we rule like רב יוסף. Rav
Yosef. Okay, so where are we?
הלכתא כוותיה דרב יוסף בזוזי. Hilchata kevatchi de-Rav Yosef be-zuzi. היכא דקמי
זוזי לוקמי. Heicha dekami zuzi lukmi. Where the money is, let it
remain.
So הני מילי דאמר ליה. Hani mili de-amar leh. Now that, so
that's it. So that's how the גמרא Gemara concludes. And now it
just has one line of clarification. והני מילי דאמר ליה הדרת וזפתינהו
מינאי. Ve-hani mili de-amar leh hadarta ve-zaftinhu minay. Now that's only if,
in a case where
the guarantor concedes, yes, you paid it up and then I re-lent
you a hundred dollars. Then he's trying to use an old שטר
shtar on a new debt. אבל אמר ליה הדרתינהו ניהלך מחמת דהוו
שייפי וסומקי. Aval amar leh hadartinhu nihalach machmat de-havu shaifei ve-sumkei. But
if he says, no, you tried to pay me back the money
you owed me, but I refused that money because it was all
worn and red and it was rusty and it was not acceptable,
so I refused it, so I took money in my hand but
I gave it back to you because it was not a new
loan because I did not accept it as payment of the old
loan, אכתי איתא לשיעבודא דשטרא. Acheti ita le-shibuda de-shtara. Then the שיעבוד
shibud of the שטר, shtar, the original שטר shtar is still in
place and the money is still owed based on the original שטר
shtar and in that case of course he can still collect with
the original שטר. shtar. Okay, we will end here with this.